all right welcome back everyone it is uh
October 10th 23 and we're in our first
discussion on chapter
two so before we jump into any questions
or
anything what is anyone's just takeaway
from chapter 2 or what were they curious
about or what something that kind of
remains with them after reading feel
free to just raise your hand hand or
just go for
it yeah hi it's Pablo here
um in the page 35 action has a pic value
and pragmatic uh value um brings Rewards
so that for me for what I'm building is
super important so yeah I I have also
some other notes but and a question over
there we can cover later so yeah for me
this is
like my pick on
this awesome yes the idea that we don't
have to coers epistemic value or
learning or Information Gain into
utility we don't have to like convert it
into utility in order for that policy to
be
selected key
aspect any other favorite quotes or fun
parts of chapter two
or parts they woke up sweating about
or I for me tying you tying this back to
the surprise and and and um maybe
elaborating on what encompasses policy I
I'm I'm putting strategy in there but I
don't know if that's correct
specifically in the low
road cool like policy
enumerates the possibilities for Action
over a given time Horizon but strategy
isn't just
enumerating branching path
so then what is strategy great
questions any other just random chapter
two
thoughts you know when it comes to this
idea of planning as inference something
that I've been just kind of thinking
about a lot lately is that um ultimately
when I do something and the best example
is just trying to walk somewhere all I
really do is to hold that conscious
intention to be somewhere and then then
I'm kind of out of the loop other than
having uh you know processing um sensory
evidence that I'm actually getting there
and as long as long as that's happening
you know I I can sort of see this this
Loop in my in my brain where I'm going
and just enjoying myself looking at
things and just thinking all kinds of
other thoughts and so on so forth and
the going kind of happens on its own all
all I really do is to have a conscious
intention I don't even necessarily have
to feel my body as it's moving if I get
into this state almost like a you know
like a walking meditation then it really
feels like you know being in a
self-driving car so it's kind of
interesting that um you know I'm
starting by understanding all of this
stuff like having a having a generative
model to notice these things in my own
awareness I'm starting to notice these
things in my own awareness and I'm
starting to be you know not only uh have
have these ideas confirmed
mathematically but also exponentially so
just a little bit weird but um really
fun
awesome cool and and also no amount of
propositional intention to walk you can
think as hard as you want I want to walk
but then actually the intention that
gets you out of the chair is something
different so what does that what does
that mean or what does that have to do
with action yeah and but but but so you
have to you have to sort of um
distinguish different kinds of intention
so like there's this there's the
intention as in kind of like it would be
nice if or like wishful thinking I I I
wish I could do this um but what I mean
by intention is a very specific mental
state and that mental state is usually
not available to you unless you start
training in meditation where it becomes
obvious that it exists so it's something
that like you know if if you think about
like think about this in from the
perspective of training neural network
for robot to do something so you know
robot will have some kind of goal in a
neural network getting to a place or
whatever so it must it must be some kind
of activation in the neural network
that's that's going to be triggering a
sequence of other activations right or a
bunch of activations that are going to
go through some kind of cycle in time
that that sort of thing and normally
that's an unconscious thing but I I
don't I don't think it has to it has to
be so and like the Buddhist meditative
practices particularly inside meditation
they specifically you know distinguish
the intention so at some point you might
be become aware like first they have an
intention to move the hand then they
have a feeling of moving the hand so as
the I'm holding the intention
and I'm getting the sensor input to
confirm that what I intended is
happening and that process is actually
uh it's possible to introspect it's
possible to to see it in your own
awareness and that's um that's that's
wonderful
really
awesome any
other opening thoughts from people just
some low road or chapter two thought or
something that they're excited about to
explore a little bit today
um the um the getting a little deeper
into what is learning versus
inference yeah multiple time
scales that computational models of
cognition play out on the fastest
sometimes being called inference the
kind of Rapid Fire neural spiking type
little bit slower attention with a
Precision waiting stepping on the gas
pulling off the gas and then a little
bit slower even
learning sometimes the whole process is
called inference sometimes inference is
only being used to refer to the kind of
like crack of the whip most rapid time
scale but what is learning the higher
order phenomena like child learning how
to read how do we connect that with a
more narrow statistical concept of
learning like we leared that the average
height of the tree in the forest was 10
feet but previously we thought it was
nine so that's
learning so is that the same as belief
updating what would anyone else say
what's what is the relationship between
learning and belief
updating I'm curious
about um if uh this system is uh
deterministic or it's more on the will
uh Free Will side
and or or nonone at
[Laughter]
all are you say saying about the belief
updating or about the active inference
about the active inference
okay you know I I like to joke that free
will you know you have you have free
will only so far as that you're free to
suffer if you really understand that
you're not a thing that you're a process
and you're totally interdependent with
everything else then you know the um the
best thing to do is always to you know
be a free energy minimizing agent to do
it in a in an optimal way if you're not
doing that in an optimal way that's
cause that will cause some friction or
or
suffering we can jump to this uh cohort
five question that's kind
of related um and then
yeah go who was
that okay um sorry oh yeah Ali go for it
uh okay so uh the relation between
belief updating and learning is that
belief updating is much more General
than just learning so uh both inference
and learning um involve belief updating
in some sense and uh this is uh one of
the probably most confusing things about
active inference modeling because most
people when it comes toar learning they
only think of belief updating uh as
apply as applied to Only The Learning
side of active inference uh but uh then
basian belief updating uh can be applied
to both inference side and uh the
learning side so they use the exact same
kind of belief basian belief updating
mechanism uh so uh we'll see how Works
uh in relation to both more explicitly
chapter
six yeah the faster inference scale is
kind of like you have the calculator
preloaded like the weights in the neuron
Network are fixed if you want to think
of it that way or the parameters are
kind of like pre-loaded and preset and
then inference is like new argument
comes in new input comes in and it just
it's like a plug-in chug that's the
faster um inferential scale which can
still result in a belief updating and
then learning is actually the change on
those weights or like the change in
that in that system how it's set up so
then influences future rounds of fast
inference
um so in that respect um it's almost
like what Kristoff was saying uh Visa
inent ality prior to a generative model
where learning is changing those
parameters you know prior to having the
generative model being able to update
that
intentionality which the which then the
belief updating happens in relation
to perhaps learning could be like what
kind of thing am I and then the faster
inference is like given the thing I am
how do I
respond and then the kind of General
theme is instead of evaluating sense
making or decision making in terms of
like maximally rewarding their cast in
terms of most
likely so instead of given what I value
what's the most
rewarding it's like given the generative
model what's the most likely
outcome and then in chapter nine we'll
look at at given what empirically did
happen what's the most likely generative
model so that's the kind of scientific
like behavioral researcher going from
the data to the most likely model and
then the other direction is from the
model generating the most likely data
and both of them are are um they're just
two two directions on the same
freeway um
all right let's look at this question
and then anyone else can like add a
question to the table or or
um write another question in the um chat
okay this means that Free Will is part
of the model question Point 2.3 the
interplay of top down and bottom up
processes distinguishes the inferential
view from alternative approaches that
only consider bottomup
processes okay probably a lot that um
could be explored here what what what
does anyone want to kind of bring in
here or say about this
section yeah that that was my question
so yeah my thought was
um if it's Boton up it would be determin
everything is around
U
it's um getting like
uh
um you are just like uh observing
and just getting the data in and you
probably won't have much um action on on
that or your agency I think we call
it and if you is top down it means that
I have an agency I'm deciding I'm I'm
modeling the the world that surrounds
me and
um yeah that was my my question my
thought and something that I
care it's very pH philosophical as well
I think and and
yeah anyone have a thought on
this yeah this is Andrew um I when I
hear this question I I just want to
recommend Eric hell's new book um I I
forget what it's called right now um
sorry I'm multitasking as usual um but
he he talks about how those uh I think
active in inference um is completely
congruent with his theory of um causal
emergence which talks about how you can
have bottom up processes and top down
and and still have some room for free
will in between um with just uh
mechanistic um uh rule folling behavior
and and so I feel like there's room for
um the philosophy to still exist Within
a um a a uh
non-dualist uh approach to um
metaphysics yeah thank you Andrew yeah
yeah thank you that makes
sense if I may add a little bit um you
know I I think it's interesting to to
consider here um sort of Steven wal's
principle of computational equivalence
so um W from based on his experience
with computation says that essentially
um there is a level in the computational
ladder ladder of sophistication and it's
actually pretty low it's it's incredibly
low that um once you hit it you're as
sophisticated computationally as any
other agent so even if you had a
completely computationally deterministic
system where everything is fixed like
the universe there is absolutely no way
you're going to be able to properly
predict um out compute um even the
simplest agents like simplest cellular
autom and so on because they are
effectively as computationally
sophisticated as you are so that gives
always rise to um
uncertainty it's it's a building feature
that uh you will not be able to compute
the perfectly a model of internal States
and this is comes up in active inference
modeling the difficulty of constructing
these generative models but it seems a
fundamental principle of nature that
that's impossible so as an agent you
know um if you're as an agent you're
kind of a controller for future State
you have an intention that you want to
achieve a future State and you're trying
trying to sort of get there but the
world that you're trying to control is
never going going to be um simply
deterministically following rules so
there's going to be resolution of some
uncertainties and I think that
resolution of uncertainties that gives
the rise to the feeling of of free will
the underlying system might be
completely deterministic but the
experience of it from from within an
um a part of it embedded in it in the
system it's always we can to feel that I
had these choices because I always had
some
uncertainty
yeah yeah yeah that that's another thing
that I Steve W from it's I I always
wonder how those these two currents are
going to cross
over yeah yeah I suspect on a machine
learning Street talk with Carl and
Steven in the coming months we'll see
though that should be quite um
interesting um Oli and then
Susan uh okay so when it comes to agency
I suppose active
inference kind of assumes that any
lifelike property including uh agency
and um many other things uh they're kind
of uh inherent to uh and uh also their
emerging property of any dynamical
non-equil Dre system uh and most of more
often than not these systems are erotic
and also they possess markup blankets so
um uh in other in other words F supposes
that
organisms have this uh goal of keeping
themselves in their uh expected States
uh or more precisely their expected
phenotypic and ontogenetic states and uh
consequently they act to minimize the
discrepancy between um the desired or
predicted the State of Affairs uh and uh
the one that they experience so uh uh to
Cote frisen himself uh it furnishes an
account of basic or biotic sentient
behavior that places agency Center Stage
so uh I believe active inference and Fe
uh is not a
deterministic uh theory of cognition at
all uh because uh as I just quoted
friston it takes agency very seriously
and uh even at the very cental stage of
the
theory thank you Oli
Susan I kind of to toe on that and you
and pose a question in terms of agency
um I you know I kind of question whether
we Rec we recognize without learning our
requisite limits which is kind of what
you I interpreted what you were talking
about um you know people go over their
requisite limits all the time it's
called anxiety it's called you know
schizophrenia whatever but but it's this
has kind of got me thinking that the
agency and the ordance is is kind of a
chicken and egg problem it's like you
know as I as I
update um is I find more freedom um
which you know freedom to choose and in
fact you know when I heard the intention
I was like well I have a choice of other
intentions so that's going to Cascade
down um that's you know that's basically
agency but but I still have to so the
belief updating or learning um you know
is going to show me new affordances but
then I need new
agency to be able to do something else
with that affordance so you know so is
it kind of a chicken and egg problem or
how does
that play out in this
model a
few narrow points but first Ali
please uh well yes actually uh there is
some concept overlap uh the FP uh with
the kind
of
ecological psychology uh Viewpoint
offered by Walsh in terms of affordances
so uh
Walsh argues that uh if an agent has a
goal it will experience its environment
as a kind of menu of affordances uh
what's in its surroundings and will and
uh whether
uh they're useful or not for attaining
that particular goal so uh the
environment agent interaction might
might be regarded as a kind of landscape
uh that uh that should be navigated to
that given end uh so in effect what it
says is uh it it posits a kind of a
optimization problem uh in which
um one might effect efficiency um uh to
play a role in determining that
trajectory so that's basically uh the
overlapping between the formulation of
Fe and uh this uh psych ecological
psychology Viewpoint or at least Walsh's
formulation of eonian affordances
because uh in both of those um cases uh
there there's this bilateral uh
interaction between
um between the environment and the agent
so as to uh the chicken egg problem uh
it cannot really be separated from each
other so uh there's this continual um a
bilateral interaction between those
two Co yeah just just to narrower points
so Pablo kind of kicked the soccer ball
off with this question about bottom up
and top down and uh these generative
models are as constructed so we could
imagine a top down constraining Force
that's just always doing it's always
clamping the same way or it's
alternating between two different top
down impositions so just the the the
mere presence of top down
forces does
not support or
reject in the system of Interest
itself the presence or absence of Free
Will defined as as someone chooses um
but by comparing a portfolio of models
it might be possible to to Garner
evidence or kind of um come to favor one
of those choices more and similarly the
um information coming bottom up
could be generated deterministically it
could be an oscillator or it could be
generated probabilistically like being
drawn from a
distribution um and that could drive
belief updating in the agent in a
nonlinear way or in a linear way so it's
like sometimes these
um adjectives that
modify the
probabilistic intern jals of the model
deterministic probabilistic all of that
um there's there's a lot of richness but
also openness in how they articulate
with um the broader philosophical
questions like Robert spolsky's current
book or it's coming out in some days or
something like that it's called
determined the science of behavior or
living without Free Will so it's like
deterministic sounds like it's going to
be addressing exact same question that
spolski is going to be addressing but
then as Kristoff pointed to even a
deterministic system of quite limited
sophistication the only way to predict
Its Behavior may be to play it out this
is kind of like turing's halting problem
like even if you're an expert in
programming you look at a piece of code
you may not be able to know a priori
whether it's going to Halt or how it's
going to act um
and then again to this kind of like more
limited generative
models have a zone of surprisal around
them but the zone of surprisal with
respect to the modeler isn't the same
thing as a truth Claim about the system
you could make um an example where the
affordance landscape is fixed like the
rat in the teamas that we'll see
later but a real rat in a te-as might
discover a new affordance like it might
find out it could roll over and you know
knock something over and then if it has
that capacity to
learn that could be model as like
expanding its e variable like expanding
its um repertoire of
affordances and then it might come to
select those so then it but the fact
that a given generative model does or
doesn't have the ability to expand its
repertoire of affordances
the real rat on the
ground just because the model can't
doesn't mean the rat can't just because
the model does doesn't mean the rat will
so that's the kind of iterated continued
engagement
and repeated modeling as a way to
develop hypotheses to to reenter the
system of Interest with action not to
just make version one of the generative
model shut the door on the
question cool
well what's another question or section
that somebody wants to look
to I'd really like to capture what you
just said about the
[Laughter]
rat
that was Pro
prolific oh mammals um let's look at
some classic
questions there's a lot here but does
anyone want to just ask one just that
comes to mind now or something they
scribbled in a margin um yeah inks and
then oh yeah inks first and then Andrew
y
so considering the difference between
model and process I'm still very far
behind all of you guys so I was
thinking the model doesn't have to be
true right it's subjective it has to
work it doesn't have to be true does the
process have some limit like do we know
absolute truth on the X asterisk the
hidden state that is asterisk as part of
the
process I'm thinking that connecting
that to
um I don't know if you guys have read
Greg's Egan uh Greg Egan's Shields
ladder where they discover a v well by
mistake through an experiment they
trigger a vacuum that is a more stable
State than our vacuum and it
starts unrolling through the universe
the way Ice Nine does in cat's cradle by
Kurds kurd vonet so I was thinking our
mod like basically inventing more and
more stable models they roll out like
that like a carpet through everything
because they're so much easier to
survive and persist
through but that's on the process side
the real real hidden state does it have
truth
yeah that that reminds me of this very
short borus um story where um you know
this is this is a somebody read chapter
6 little bit too literally um and they
wanted a perfect
map and then it it came to just like you
said inks it came to unfurl over the
whole
territory until it just blurred with
with the
territory another answer to that is um
xstar the the generative
process using the way that the textbook
talks about it though Oli may may bring
up a very Salient point is um still
something that's proposed by the
model and so xstar could be said to have
like a local truth let's just say we
have um you know an air condition
turning on or off agent kind of regular
setting like that thermometer sense
readings making inference about
temperature in the room taking action to
turn on the air conditioner and then we
have like the generative process which
is giving rise to the temperature
readings now all of that is like a
local constructed
truth but just making some sort of
function to describe how
temperature um plays out in that um
modeled room again that doesn't mean
that the real
room has that
feature
Oli uh well yes there so there's
actually this um kind of criticism or uh
debate going on around FP um about
whether it's uh too General to be uh
realistic uh scientific model of uh the
agents or more specifically cognitive
agents because on one hand um it kind of
puts everything in a a great degree of
abstraction uh to the extent that it may
not be able to answer some uh some
concrete um questions about the
biological or the bi olical nature of
the uh agent or the real world
situations of the agent so for instance
uh there was this a paper by uh coloman
palasio from uh
2020 one uh
namely uh let me yeah non-equilibrium
thermodynamics in the free energy
principle in biology uh in which um they
explicitly put forward this criticism
around FP as being to too General to be
useful for modeling any real world or or
concrete uh biological problems but on
the other hand uh FP never claimed
otherwise because uh according to the fe
uh any or a given non-equilibrium system
uh with a Target State um will all would
always seek the most efficient route uh
and this route would typically uh be the
one
defined by considerations of uh the
gradient descent or in other words the
path uh through all the available
configuration space um uh that follows
the uh steepest route uh to the minimum
so uh again in this view uh it's it's
not
even uh explicit whether the agency or
all the other Concepts we're talking
about are real or or the apparent
properties of the agents uh
so um more to the point uh I believe uh
Fe and active inference can be more
congruent with a structural realism uh
view of the uh philosophy of science as
opposed to just um old-fashioned or
traditional uh real pure realism or
naive realism of U view of the science
uh and in this regard uh Frist
coauthored some papers with M Majid
Benny
uh and they argue for this view of f as
uh as a kind of view
that that is more congruent with a
structural realism and particularly
ontological uh structural
realism awesome
Kristoff you know I just want to say
that um holding on to any kind of notion
of Truth U I think the the best the best
thing that ever happened to me in my
life is I decided that just there is
there are no truths there are just
simply models within models within
models and you can sort of see it in in
the temperature example temperature is
not real it's a virtual variable
literally what what the physicist would
call it right it's a um it's a way of
cor spraining all the um interactions
between gas molecules in such a way that
we that we can measure so we have
something that persists for time that we
we can observe but you're you're never
really looking at reality and if you if
you go down you know this rabbit hole
then ultimately you will arrive at
something that like there is some
computational say W's perspective on
this am very fond of that one there is
some computational model that's running
all possible computations so what truth
would be in that in that kind of context
would be that the the the shortest
description um the shortest possible
program that gives rise eventually to
what what you're observing but because
un because Universe because everything
is kind of like interdependent you're
never going to be able to to to to I
think I think you're never going to be
able to separate um you know and say
like oh this is this is the the the the
the the true process that gave rise to
to to this observation it's going to be
some kind of interplay of all kinds of
computational process
all all running kind of independently
so um you know in so far as I think this
is why there there's this difficulty in
in writing down these generative models
of all these possible um Poss when we
have this um you know probability of of
our priors because there's absolutely no
way to to to know what these priors will
be we can only make um uh you know
guesses of what the what the range of
these um uh values uh can taken and
adapt as as um evidence evidence as
observations are flowing
in
cool also on this kind of generative
model generative process uh point this
is one great great
question
um in figure
22 and throughout this
textbook pains are made to distinguish
the generative model from the generative
process and it is a useful distinction
to understand the process that gives
rise to the
observations the modeled process that
gives rise to the observation so the
kind of like digital niche of this
generative model of the agent um and yet
in a guest stream we saw a slight
different perspective or at least way to
talk about this when Maxwell presented
and utilized this bracket to cover the
entire generative model including
external
States again those that give rise to
sensory States and at this time step in
the published transcript Ali asks this
question very specifically so there's of
course many ways to speak this or any
dialect but within this textbook
generative process is used to refer to
the process external to the
agent the particular states of the agent
blanket and internal the external states
are described as generative process
giving rise to the
observations and not influencing the
actual fundamentals of the particular
partition but rather just using a
different natural language to describe
it it is also becoming common to
describe the generative model as
describing
all the necessary and
sufficient statements that the modeler
makes about the entire
scenario and not distinguishing so
much as to what's the generative process
in the generative model
one piece of uh I guess support for like
this kind of just use generative model
to describe it all first off it's
simpler also if you have two agents in
conversation
then of course one of them is the
generative process to the other and vice
versa and so just In The Same Spirit of
like well states of the world or aspects
of the world let alone the map they're
not tagged as like sensory or action or
internal or external those qualifiers
are always relative to which node is
being called the internal State and then
the rest of the blanket is just
trivially assigned from there so it
doesn't make sense to like say well this
desk is the external State it's like
well but it's its own internal state if
I chose to model it from that side or
with respect to the wall behind it it's
the blanket State between me and the
wall
so using generative Model A little bit
more
broadly seems to be a little bit of a
development that has unfolded over the
uh cohor and years
Susan yeah I mean the way ask see it if
I you correct me if I'm not looking at
it correctly but you know when you do
research you have to decide what your
ontology or epistemology is going to be
when you apply it um and um and you
always provide context for that so this
kind of is above that in my mind in fact
you know we and you and I've had a
conversation because I yeah I want to
make sure that the that it's um that
it's ideology free
um
because you know I see way too much um
you know um BS especially in management
science that you know is just embedded
with somebody's ideology and it's taken
as fact so it's kind of what I like
about the model um that um brings me to
um you the the marov
blanket and um you where you so in that
sense of you the uh the model the
generative model where where does the
Markoff blanket extend because it was a
little confusing reading
it is that just confirm for me though am
I looking at it correctly in terms of it
being a
theistic that's why I posted that in the
comments because that's what I copied
from chapter 10 I think
cool maybe post what what page you you
found it on but it's it's a great quote
um features are not intrinsically on the
blanket or internal or
external there's a base graph that
conveys whatever variables are being
included
whatever Quantified aspects are under
consideration or or formalized doesn't
have to be a number it could be like
categorical but whatever is being
brought whatever Lego pieces are coming
on the table and how those Lego pieces
are connected that's the base graph and
then whatever node or cluster of nodes
is being selected as the internal States
the blanket is just all that surround
that and so when we're taking this kind
of agentic view or cybernetic view on
cognitive ecosystems then
the blanketing states just to give a
first pass can be understood in terms of
sensory data so anything that you would
record with a sensor and then the
outgoing dependencies are actions
anything that would be described by the
affordances of an
actuator so to add so to add build on
what Ink's question was would the
Markoff blanket be the same for if I'm
doing let's say I am doing a research in
a modeling project would I use the same
Markoff blanket for the process and the
model or would the model or would the
process change the
blanket the the final
mod just giving a narrower answer
because I I I know that's something that
could be explored at Great depth if you
made a generative model with a fixed
Mark marov blanket then it would be
fixed if you said our room has a
thermometer and an arm that's an
actuator and you know different data are
going to come in and the arm is going to
do different things well then the the
kind of um scheme of the blanket
wouldn't
change but you might want to be
interested modeling the transition from
that room deciding that it should put
out a second thermometer at which point
the scheme of it would change okay and
so then you'd be outside that room be
like oh they literally just went from
having one thermometer to two
thermometers and then you could
postulate cognitive models that happened
inside of that room you'd say maybe it's
like there they had an affordance to add
a thermometer and they selected that
affordance does that answer your
question better
in now I have more more questions but I
don't want to stir more trouble
here what what else is the end of a
session for other than stirring trouble
um so because you were talking about
being in the room can I just roll with
it of
course you were talking about being in
the room and then a second th
thermometer and I was thinking of as an
agent this I don't think this is about
this chapter but as an agent as my mark
of blanket is like I'm looking at the
screen right now but then have a flutter
in my heart and I'm like oh no am I
having a heart attack in my mark of
blanket is that a separate Mark of
blanket where now I'm modeling myself
very close and tight around my heart
then I hear the door knock and oh I have
a package from Ukraine and I run like
now my My atten sl Mark of blanket is
all the way my apartment and the door to
the outside world where someone is
knocking are these different am I
switching
between different Mark of blankets or is
the mark of blanket moving with my
attention
regime great question well to the
wandering blankets and um blankets that
are not sort of one or zero but can be
on a Continuum or a blanket index
certainly some of the most recent work
is addressing that I'll just leave that
there but to the interception question
um in chapter six when we're exploring
ing how to construct these generative
models an example of of Sensor Fusion is
provided so let's just say that a given
body has some interceptive Sensations
like heart rate and then some
exteroceptive sensory capacities like
hearing and vision and so on um those
are kind of like all open even when you
close your eyes you're still getting
visual input and and usually it's
modeled not as changes in the blanket
but in changes in attention like you
still have proprio receptors in your
foot but you're not paying attention to
them you're not attending to them which
is to say it's as if this the data
coming from them are not making a
difference to belief updating if you're
not paying attention to
something it is not having consequence
it's its differences are not making a
difference and then regimes of ention
describe the way that in this kind of
multimodal
setting um the spotlight of attention
might focus on a given sensory
modality and so that is usually modeled
more as an attention modulation task
within a fixed marov blanket schema
rather
than um changes to the the schem of the
blanket itself
Kristoff so you know this makes me think
that um having this sort of uh you know
explicit model of attention within um a
fixed Mark of blanket it's really it's
really Mark of blanket is a kind of like
a convenient
um it's it's an idea it's a convenient
idea for modeling to to make this
separation but it's not actually
something that that is real there is
um any boundary that you can find and
say like yes this is definitely a
boundary between the internal and
external States and this reent work on
on on on on moving blankets I think I
think what we're eventually going to
realize is that it's there's just a
Precision parameter there as well like
how how how how thick I want my my
market blanket to be and um it's for for
the convenience of describing certain
phenomena at certain temporal scales it
simply makes it makes sense to make an
assumption that there is a separation
between these internal and external
States but in reality if you look at
it you know at all temporal scales you
will find that there is the the the
separation is you know it's not really
there it's a it's a it's um it's it's
invented so this you know it's kind of
like uh this is the way I sort of
understood the the the Buddhist concept
of relativity
everything is sort of relative and I I
put myself in a frame of reference and I
said well within this frame of reference
these are internal these are external
States and then I have and and and I
have a way of of looking at them to make
sense of them if if I didn't have the
ability then it might be difficult to to
be able to make sense sense of the world
if I if I if I can't make this partition
but is the partition real I I you know
personally I didn't think so it's just
it's just a point of
view thank you um
Andrew
yeah a couple of riffs on um what's been
said uh one like the the the finding
your own Markov blanket I feel like is a
little bit of a um hopeless cause
because it it's it's very likely that
you are many
nested um you contain Markoff blankets
all the way down um and
there's um a lot of complex phenomena
and interior modeling going on um in
terms of coming to grips with that one
resource I'd like to recommend is if
anyone's seen the book The Mind
illuminated by Dr John
Yates um it's it's kind of a good
rationalist take on a meditation
practice that uh kind of lets you come
to grips with there's probably multiple
agentic things happening in your brain
um another thing that uh was just kind
of wow to me that I just wanted to gush
about about this chapter is um I've been
trying to sort of come to grips with
what normativity means in a um sort of
non-dist agentic um frame of reference
and there was a couple quotes at the end
of this chapter one of which is in
active inference the identity of an
agent is isomorphic with its priors that
just like I was like oh all right that
kind of puts it all together and um kind
of um to to get that um pitched up they
start with expected states are preferred
and include the organism's conditions
for survival EG Niche specific goal
States whereas their opposite surprising
states are dispreferred in this way by
find fulfilling their expectations
active inference agents ensure their own
Survival so it just that phenomena one
thing
um your Beijing priors are your
normative order which um I've been
searching for what does a normative
order mean especially within the context
of
um sort of
a small agent um trying to find
relevance in in the cognitive limits of
finding relevance there and um I feel
like this is um this is the right
approach also one more
thing with the um free uh not
variational free energy but um um the
the planning one expected free energy
um we were talking about um what s the
way it includes both
epistemic and um preference value in the
same equation I I feel like as a group
we really need to um tackle that as a
and realizing that maybe a lot of
our preconceptions that we've been
grappling with during this meeting are
really summed up with understanding that
itself that that it all fits both
epistemic ontological in the same sort
of optimization
framework so that's that's just me um
riffing on this great comments equation
2.5 and equation
2.6 are like the heart of the heart of
active inference we have the real time
sense
making about incoming sense data and
beliefs and then we have the prospective
which not all agents even need to be
modeled as doing the
prospective unified imperative for
pragmatic and
epistemic
outcomes
and that's the heart and that's the
mystery and that's um like the part that
we don't need to reinvent and then all
the work is in getting it into a form
getting the system of Interest into a
form where you just press play on those
equations um Ali and then any final
comments that people
have thank you uh yeah uh
regarding whether or not or to what
extent markup blankets are code UN code
real uh it's probably worth uh keeping
in mind
uh that markup blankets are uh more
precisely they're not necessarily spao
temporal boundaries but rather uh they
draw boundaries in state space or in
other words in the space of all possible
configurations uh
so uh it's true that sometimes it
manifests itself as a kind of spatial
temporal boundary such as uh the cell
membrane
uh but uh more often than not uh we
don't need to consider markup blankets
as uh kind of purely physical or spatio
temporal boundaries so uh yes it's a
kind of uh modeling technique uh but but
uh in terms of its
mathematical um reality it is as true as
any other mathematical
models cool
well very fun the low
road is it a bumpy road is it a smooth
Road what is it like I don't know um but
that was our first discussion on it next
week at the earlier time we will check
back so it would be epic if people just
right in the coming minutes or in the
coming week add a few more questions to
chapter five questions where we'll look
at the bigger questions table too um in
cohort 4 we'll be heading into chapter
eight on continuous time generative
models and uh we'll have next week on
chapter two then head into three so
thank you all the game goes on so see
you next
time thanks everyone bye bye